can
get here. Right? I like to walk around.
So,
we've talked about neural networks all
semester long
and we've focused on how we can do
things like classification and
prediction and time series analysis and
modeling language and things like that,
right?
We're going to start with a new problem.
So,
and that is
how to learn to generate stuff, right?
We've already done this for language,
but it was a kind of abstract concept.
Language is something we might
understand, but what about images? You
are given a large collection of images
of faces for instance,
and from these this collection of
images, can you try to learn a model
that can generate can can draw new
faces? Guys, shut your laptops, please.
>> [clears throat]
>> Yeah.
You mind? Yeah.
Okay, thank you, right? So,
what does it [snorts] mean to be able to
draw a new face?
To be able to draw a new face,
essentially what you're learn what
you're saying is that I want to learn
the distribution of
face images
and somehow and I want to be able to
draw samples from this distribution.
Question is, what is this distribution?
Obviously, it's not something nice and
tidy like a Gaussian, it's probably
something very ugly. How do you
characterize it? And even if you manage
to characterize this really hideous
distribution, how do you come up with a
mechanism for drawing a sample from this
distribution?
Or a collection of landscapes, right?
Again, if I wanted learn see a picture
whole bunch of landscape pictures, and
then figure out how to draw new
landscape pictures. How can I learn to
do this? How do I learn the distribution
of landscapes, and then how do I learn
to sample from it?
Now, in all of this there's a there's
something that we sort of uh
uh pin our
principles on. And that is that anytime
you have data of a very specific kind,
it means it doesn't belong to any other
kind, right? A picture of a face is not
a landscape. A picture of a face is not
white noise. It's not a It's not a It's
not a spacecraft. So,
we're actually eliminating
possibilities.
When you eliminate possibilities, what
is it you do?
So, the space of all possibilities is
everything.
When you eliminate some when you impose
some restrictions, when you eliminate
degrees of freedom, you're sort of you
sort of keep restricting the
possibilities. Every time you restrict
the possibilities, you're saying, "That
portion of the space, that's not faces.
That's not possible, right?" The only
thing that occupies all space, what
would it be?
Anyone?
Take a guess, guys. It's noise. Yes,
noise, right? If it's unstructured, it's
noise. If it's structured, it's not
There are some things it simply cannot
do. By the time you get to something to
be sufficiently structured,
what you will find is that all the data
of this particular category lie in a
very small region of the overall space.
Typically, the volume of the space that
they lie in
is going to be so small that it's going
to close to zero, right?
And so, the prin- idea here is that
there is some underlying manifold, some
curved surface, which represents the
structure for this data, and all data
from that class lie on or close to that
surface. Anytime you want to draw
something
that belongs to that class, you're going
to have to pick something from that
surface. But then, how do you
characterize the surface? How do you
characterize this manifold? And how do
you draw from it?
So, we've already seen one way of
characterizing manifolds. If you were
there in the last class,
we we learned about autoencoders.
And what did we say the decoder in an in
an autoencoder did?
Anybody remember what did it do?
Anyone?
So, it's here on the slide, so you can
you can help me, right?
What did we say the decoder of an
autoencoder did?
Hm?
Someone.
Anybody on Zoom? Do you want to answer
this?
Linear classification.
So, what we said, okay, if the
autoencoder had linear activations, what
did it do?
We discussed this in class. Hopefully,
you were paying attention.
What does an autoencoder with only
linear activations do?
Do you remember that?
Hm?
So, maybe someone on Zoom is an- is
answering. Can you check?
It performs principal component
analysis. You remember that, right? And
so, the what happens if I remove the
modify the linear activations and can
make them non-linear?
What was what was it doing?
Someone on Zoom is answering, I'm sure.
It performs principal manifold analysis.
It actually finds the principal manifold
that the data lie on, and then
uh represents everything as being on
this manifold. So, we already have a
mechanism for capturing the underlying
manifold. We saw this, and that's what
we used in my little toy examples where
I learned an autoencoder from say the
examples of saxophone music. And then
when I took the decoder and just excited
it using any odd excitation, it produced
outputs that somewhat sounded somewhat
like a saxophone, right?
Or
uh if I wanted now use the same
mechanism for drawing pictures of faces,
I could train an autoencoder on lots and
lots of face images.
And then I could use the decoder.
If I do it right, the decoder is going
to learn the manifold of all faces, the
small section of the space on which
faces lie. And then when I excite the
decoder,
it's going to generate something lying
on the face manifold.
And this is what we are going to be able
to use. But then we have a problem.
And the problem we saw in the last
class,
uh so, you know, we can just use the
decoder to generate more faces.
The problem was this,
that when I trained an autoencoder,
I did not have any constraint on what
the hidden latent variable could be.
So, the way our autoencoder was trained,
you had an encoder.
Your data went in.
You had a Z. This was the latent
variable.
That was what the the variable that
connected the encoder to the decoder.
And then this variable went into the
decoder
to generate data all over again.
But we didn't say anything about what
the Z could be, right? And if we train
this properly, we know we know that this
decoder is only able to generate data on
the manifold that
the data lie on. So, in our example over
here, the data all lay lay on a on a
spiral.
So, if my little hidden latent variable
is unidimensional, just a scalar,
that means that the decoder is going to
basically fold a one-dimensional space.
What is a one-dimensional space? It's a
line, right? And it's going to fold this
line to match the data as much as
possible. It's going to learn the
spiral, which is indeed what it does.
But what this entire structure is
missing is a restriction on Z.
So, if these were my Zs,
and this is my Z axis, I pass all of my
training data through my
uh autoencoder.
But since we have no restriction on what
the Z is or can or must be, you might
find that for part of the data it's
using Zs in this range.
For some other part of the data, it's
using Zs in this range. And then all the
rest of it goes for the for the rest of
the Zs.
Now, it's only on these Zs that you're
going to get
the spiral.
For Zs and Zs that were not seen or very
rare in the training data,
you have no idea what what it's going to
which It's still going to be a
one-dimensional curve. You have no idea
what that curve is going to be, right?
Which is why you have the strange
situation over here. Most of it becomes
goes around the spiral, but then here
and out here, those are Zs that were not
seen in the training data.
If I want to use this mechanism
to generate images of faces, would this
work in this naive manner? If I just
trained an autoencoder and then began
feeding random Zs, am I likely to get
faces? What do you think?
Can you speak up? No. No, why not?
Uh it's not enough to carry the
information
It doesn't tell you what Zs
are are going to produce valid faces,
right? Even in that low-dimensional
space, the volume of Z that actually
will generate a face is going to be very
small.
More often than not, if I randomly
choose a Z from it, what's going to come
out is going to be any odd thing. So, we
need a way of constraining the Zs so
that we know exactly what Zs to feed
for the model to generate faces. Am I
making sense to everybody, right?
Okay.
Guys, since this is my first in-person
class, I'm going to ask ask you to yell
out yes every time you understand what I
say, and I will keep I will not continue
till I hear a really loud chorus,
because that's the only way I make sure
that you guys are awake. Even if you
fall asleep, everybody else's yeses will
wake you up.
Okay. Now,
here's your first poll.
>> I'm falling behind it.
I follow another strange rule in class.
The first person to shut their laptop
tells me that the poll is answered.
They're timing it. So,
Lindy over there thinks she's answered
the poll.
Right?
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, guys, you're out of time, right?
Shut your laptops. Can anybody answer
the question? First one, true or false?
Someone on Zoom, true or false?
Is anyone replying?
No? Guys, what happened?
True, okay. Do you agree that this is
true?
Okay, can everybody say true together? 1
2 3.
Thank you, right? What about the second
question? What is Which are the true
statements?
What is the true dimensionality of the
manifold?
Anyone?
Second one. Second one. It's no greater
than the dimensionality of the latent
variable. So, here's what happens,
right? If I take If I If I multiply
a two-dimensional vector by a four cross
two matrix, the result is in
four-dimensional space. But all the data
are still going to lie in a
two-dimensional plane on the
four-dimensional space. You know this
from linear algebra, right? This is not
special There's nothing special about
linear transforms. Even if it's a
non-linear transform,
all the non-linear transform does is to
fold the sheet. So, if I take an
N-dimensional space
and then put it through some kind of a
transform, it gives me an M-dimensional
output output where M is greater than N,
the result is still going to lie on an
N-dimensional surface, which could be
planar or curved in the M-dimensional
space. And so, that's what That's why
we're able to use the structure, right?
It's going to be a manifold, but the
dimensionality of the manifold is the
same as that of Z.
Okay. And this is what we're actually
using.
And so, now,
we've decided I'm going to assign some
dimensionality to Z.
This is my hypothesis that the data lies
close to some Z-dimensional surface in
the larger space, right?
Images Images are million dimensional if
you have a million pixels. If you have
10 million pixels, they're 10 million
dimensional. But the actual images of
faces are going to be maybe on some
three or four or 100-dimensional surface
in this million-dimensional space, which
means Z has to be have
100 dimensions, right? So,
except we have no restriction on what Z
could be. It's a huge space. How do I
impose a restriction on Z?
I can do this externally. And the way I
can do it is say, my Z has to follow a
standard Gaussian distribution. This is
my way of imposing a restriction because
the model allows you to do so.
So, Z Z is drawn from
standard Gaussian, right? And now, if I
train the model properly, I can draw
samples from the standard Gaussian and
pass it through the decoder, and it's
going to generate faces.
So, how exactly do we do this? Is this
making sense?
Right, yeah. Thank you, right? So, how
exactly does one train the autoencoder
to do this?
That is where things get hideous.
We're done with the easy portion of the
lecture. The rest of the lecture you're
going to have to pour coffee into your
eyes to stay awake. Please do so, okay?
Uh So, how does one train an autoencoder
to ensure that the hidden representation
has a specific distribution, such as,
you know, standard Gaussian? There's
nothing magical about standard
Gaussians. You could use any odd
representation for this for the
distribution of the latent variable.
Why do you think we use Gaussians?
Anybody? Any idea why we would use a
Gaussian as opposed to something else?
You look like you know the answer. I
don't know the answer. Okay. There was a
look of knowledge on your face. So,
anybody?
It's easier mathematically. It's easier
mathematically, that's right. The
Gaussian is the most unstructured
distribution data you can think of.
Because if you have a bunch of samples,
they all converge to normal.
And that's Okay, that's a consequence,
right? So, a Gaussian of all possible
distributions, the Gaussian is the one
with the highest entropy for a given
variance.
It's the most unstructured data. And
that's why when I keep adding more and
more noisy data,
the structure keeps decreasing, and then
it's going to become Gaussian because
that's the most unstructured you can be.
So, if I don't want to make assumptions
about my latent distribution, having a
Gaussian distribution for it makes the
most sense.
That's why we start off with a Gaussian,
right? If you know something about it,
then you could use the other
distribution, right?
So, here's what a standard Gaussian
looks like.
It's
You know what a Gaussian is. It's this
nice bell shape. If I have an
N-dimensional Gaussian, it's going to be
an It's going to be an N-dimensional
bell curve. It's going to be a bell
curve along every dimension. All the
dimensions are independent of one
another, so the joint distribution of Z1
and Z2 is going to be the probabilities
of
the product of the probabilities of Z1
and Z2. They're all independent. And
each component by itself is isotropic,
meaning it has zero mean and unit
variance.
So,
the probability the formula for it
is 1 over square root of 2 pi raised to
D. D is the dimensionality of the
uh variable. And this is the nice bit.
That's e raised to minus minus .5 norm
of Z squared. So, what this really means
is that the logarithm of the Gaussian
falls off as a quadratic.
So, the Gaussian basically follows the
exponent of a quadratic. And Now, we
know something about quadratics. What
else do we know about quadratics?
If you can dig back into your memory, we
mentioned it.
Anyone?
We said that of all convex functions,
it's the nicest, right?
Because it's got just the right
properties. And so,
there's the mathematical advantage to
having Gaussians as well.
And so, here's what I'm going to say.
I'm going to say that my encoder and
decoder must
be such that they reconstruct the input,
but on top of that, I'm going to impose
the constraint that the variable Z that
connects the encoder to the decoder is a
Gaussian.
How do I
enforce this restriction on Z?
We can do it in one of two ways.
I can take large quantities of the data,
and I can look at the distribution of
all of the of the Zs for all of the
data. That's going to have some
distribution, and then I can try to
minimize the KL divergence between that
distribution and the standard Gaussian.
If I do that, then the distribution of
Zs is going to become
>> [snorts]
>> Gaussian, right? But there's another way
of doing it, which is the easier way,
which is to say that if a variable is
Gaussian,
then [snorts] an expectation the log
likelihood of data from that of
instances of that variable
computed using a Gaussian
is going to be higher
than if you compute it using any other
distribution. Because if you compute it
using any other distribution, that's
probably going to assign too low
probabilities to data that are actually
high probability or too high
low probability. Either way, you're
going to get chewed, right? So, this is
the second one.
You want to maximize the log likelihood
of the Zs as computed from a standard
Gaussian,
or alternately, minimize the negative
log likelihood.
This is something that we use in machine
learning, you know, statistics all the
time, right?
So, let's take a look at how this works.
If again, go back and this is the
formula for the Gaussian. If I take the
log Gaussian, it's minus .5 D log of 2
pi. This is not
a function of any variable. So, all
you're left with is
you know,
since I'm taking the negative log
likelihood, plus .5 norm Z squared.
Beautiful. That's a quadratic, right?
And so,
I can just say, "Okay, I'm going to try
to minimize
the norm Z squared,
which which is the basically the output
of the encoder. The .5 is just a scaling
factor. I can get rid of it, right? And
so, the overall loss that I would have
is something of this kind. I want to
minimize the error between
what the decoder reconstructs and what
it started off with,
while also minimizing the squared norm
of Z.
And this lambda is
uh basically a balancing factor, which
decides determines how you balance these
two
uh
components of the loss.
Now, would this work? Do you think Do
you guys think think this would work?
Anyone?
Yeah. Uh I don't think so, really, cuz
you're just trying to make Zs as small
as possible.
>> Exactly, right? If this
What this is going to do is keep pushing
all the Zs towards zero. In the limit,
you know, if you do a perfect job, all
Zs are zero, right? Or very close to
zero. If I begin randomly sampling
Zs from a standard Gaussian,
that's not really going to give me Most
of the Zs that I see are not something
that I would have seen in the training
data because this is pushing all the Zs
towards zero. They're all going to
become very small, right?
So, we need This mechanism is not going
to work. What we really need is this
first mechanism. Minimize the KL
divergence between the distribution of Z
and the standard Gaussian.
And that's where
it becomes kind of ugly mathematically.
Now, it's not really bad. It's not hard
math. It's not painful. It's just
painful because it's tedious.
But uh you know, your good fortune is
that I'm going to breeze through it in
one lecture and then you'll never see it
again. Anyway.
So,
here's your second problem.
Too early in the morning.
>> [laughter]
>> It's a week better in class though, so
that's good.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, guys. It's just
two true false questions. What are the
answers? What's the answer to the first
question? Anybody?
>> [snorts]
>> Second one, Alva?
Uh
I said false.
You're right, right. A regular auto
encoder trained to also minimize the
length of the hidden latent
representation implicitly assumes that
the Z's come from an isotropic Gaussian
and
the output
of this AE is still going to lie on a
low-dimensional manifold because the
manifold itself is decided by the
dimensionality of Z and nothing to do
with the distribution of Z itself,
right?
But this is not going to work, right?
This does not adequately account for the
variation in the data. It will push all
training data to simply have a very
small Z with no
with very low variance. And that's not
going to work. I mean, we have a bunch
of examples. I'm not going to show them
simply because
A, I don't have them on the slides. B,
I'm out of time.
Now,
so let's go back and
start all over again, right?
Is everything I've said so far
making sense to you?
Right. Thank you. That's very nice of
you. So, the generative portion of the
model,
this is the decoder, right? This is the
one that takes in a Z and generates
data. Now, once again, I have my problem
was to
learn a distribution for say faces
and then somehow come up with a
mechanism
for drawing from this distribution.
And the way we did this was to realize
that
the
set of all faces lies on a
low-dimensional manifold in the
high-dimensional space. You can have 100
million pixels in your faces in your
image,
but if you take all consider all face
images, they lie on a very thin
low-dimensional manifold in this 100
million dimensional space, right? So,
how do I characterize it and how do I
sample from it?
And the mechanism we chose was to say
that I'm going to start off with a Z
which belongs to
say a 100 dimensional space if that's
what I think my the true degrees of
freedom in faces are, right? And so then
this
I'm going to put
through some function. This is some
network
which outputs X. And this network is
going to take this 100 dimensional sheet
and fold it
so that the folded sheet now represents
the manifold of faces.
And then subsequently, anytime I draw a
Z from here and pass it through this
guy, it's going to pick a point from the
manifold of faces. And the problem we
are left with is, you know, how do I
choose which Z? I know that it's going
to be on the right surface,
but I still need to be on the correct
location on that surface. And everything
is about trying to figure out, you know,
how to pinpoint the Z's, right?
So,
when I do this
using simply, you know, when I just
minimize the norm of Z, all you'll find
is that for Z equals zero, it produces a
pretty good
uh picture of an average face. But if
you go off zero, it's going to produce
nonsense because
you know, it hasn't learned, right?
Now,
again, the decoder we know can only
generate data on a low-dimensional
manifold of the space of the same
dimensionality as the input. So, it
transforms the planar input space
to a curved manifold in the output
space.
The moment you curve things,
why Gaussian? I can use any other
distribution, right? But whatever the
distribution is, if I have a sheet of
this kind, right? This is my planar
sheet
and I have a Gaussian on it
and then I begin folding and twisting
and turning it.
It's going to be a curved surface, but
is the distribution still going to be
Gaussian?
What do you guys think?
So, it's going to lie on the surface,
right? Something that only lies on the
surface and it's twisted and turned can
be anything. There's no restriction at
anymore. I can take a circle and if I
twist it and turn it and warp the line,
it it can look like an ellipse. It can
look like two pinched
blobs. It can look like any other thing.
And so if I learn the function properly,
it's going to learn to manipulate this
Gaussian so that what comes out on the
outside looks like the distribution of
faces on that
surface. And so
uh that's how
a mechanism called reparameterization
where you start up start start off with
a standard distribution, somehow modify
the data so that you end up with a new
distribution, okay?
So,
here's the thing. I don't know what the
distribution of the actual latent
distribution is. What is the What is the
dimensionality of the manifold that
faces lie on?
I am going to take a guess.
Odds are my guess is guess is wrong.
So,
even if I get the best 100 dimensional
fit
to this manifold, a lot of data will not
lie on it because the data itself might
be say 120 dimensional or 1,000
dimensional. It's still much lesser than
the million dimensions of the image,
but I have missed
the manifold itself, right? And number
one, and number two, even if I somehow
magically manage to capture the exact
dimensionality of the manifold,
the uh faces are not going to lie
exactly on the manifold. They're going
to be a bit of a fuzz around it because,
you know, if you take a picture of a
photograph of a person,
there's a lot out there that's not
all face, right? I mean, you're going to
have small variations. And so, our
simple model doesn't capture any of this
variation of the manifold which could be
because A, you got the dimensionality
wrong. B, the data just varied, right?
So, how how do you capture it?
>> [clears throat]
>> You're going to assume I need to account
for the off-manifold
variation.
I have the data. I will assume that my
face is 100 dimensional
or they live in a 100 dimensional space,
but in reality they live in 180
dimensions, right?
Somehow I must account for this
error off the surface so that I can
learn this 100 dimensional manifold
properly.
The way I will account for it is to say
there is a noise
and this noise
is something that I add
to data points on the manifold to get
real faces. That making sense to you
guys? Right? And so,
this noise, since again I cannot make
any assumptions, this noise I will
assume is full dimensional. It doesn't
have any low dimensionality to it. It's
in the entire million dimensions or
whatever the dimensionality of my
dimensionality of my pictures is.
And so, now if I train the model,
there's something
crazy that can happen.
I can just somehow magically push all
the information about faces into the
noise.
That's not a good thing, right? Then the
model itself has learned nothing about
faces.
So, I have to minimize this noise so
that the model learns everything as much
as it can about faces.
Making sense to you guys everybody?
Right? And so,
you want to
train the model to minimize this noise
so that it has captured the principal
manifold most effectively. This is the
smallest amount of noise to be added
such that the distribution at the output
fully explains the distribution of the
training data. Furthermore, you're going
to assume that the district that the
noise that you're adding
is Gaussian.
Why would you assume that the noise is
Gaussian? Anyone?
We mentioned something about it briefly
just a little while ago.
If the noise were not Gaussian,
it means the noise has
structure.
Correct? If the noise has structure,
that's something the model can learn.
The model should capture all the
structure in your data.
If it does a good job of capturing all
the structure in your data, all that
remains is unstructured Gaussian noise.
So, you're going to assume the noise is
Gaussian. That making sense everybody?
Right? And so,
now
if I'm adding noise to the output of the
model, I feed some Z into the decoder,
some E comes out. I'm adding noise. The
output is no longer deterministic
because the noise is being drawn from
some random distribution, right? And so,
can you
shut your laptop at the back, please?
Yeah. Rules of the class. Laptops are
shut, right?
And so,
this decoder is now what we will call a
generative model
for the data. It has a generative story
for how the data are produced. There's a
K dimensional vector drawn from a
standard K dimensional Gaussian is
passed through the data with the model.
The result lies on a K dimensional
space. Then a full rank low amplitude
noise is added to it to generate the
final data, the actual distribution is a
fuzzy region around this manifold.
Now, we want to train the model.
If I knew, how do I train the model?
Now, this is this becomes a standard
regression problem. In any regression
problem, you're going to assume that
there's some residual noise and it's
Gaussian, right? And the reason you
assume it's Gaussian is that's when most
of the structure is pushed into the
model.
So, we know how to train regression
models.
For regression models, I know the input
that goes in, I know the output
X and I train the model to minimize
the error that you get when the input Z
is pushed through the model
to compute an output. That's a standard
regression model, right?
I could do that over here.
Except, I don't know the value of Z for
any input. For every input, if I knew
the value of Z, I could take the XZ
pairs,
the collection, push them through a
regression standard regression training
and I just learn my model.
What can I do if I don't know Z?
Anybody?
I don't know Z, right? What can I do?
Again, this is a regression model, if
it's making sense to you guys, right? My
regression model has something of this
kind. Your standard regression you'd be
given your training data would be X
Z.
Then you put your Z through some model.
It's going to give you some X hat. You
have the true X.
You minimize the error. This is how you
train your regression, right? This would
be easy.
Z is the latent variable, is a position
on the manifold.
If I had the Z for every X, I could
train this net this network, right?
I don't have Z. What can I do?
Estimate it. I can guess it.
Right? And so,
we don't have Z, so we're going to guess
the Z.
And that Z, the guess for the Z is what
comes from the encoder.
Making sense to everybody?
So, now, if I look at it this way, I
have to guess the Z, right?
Now, how do I guess the Z?
From the X. If I have a current encoder,
I can push the back decoder, I can push
the X back through the decoder to get
the Z.
And now I have a guess for the Z, right?
This is a standard approach. I'm going
to have a current guess for the model.
Then, use it for every X, I can push the
data back reverse through the model to
get the guess for the Zs. I'm going to
have a collection of X's X's and Z's
now. I can go back and re-estimate my
regression. I can keep repeating this
process. And eventually, when the thing
stops changing, I know I've learned a
proper regression. That's basically what
we want to do over here. And except
pushing the model data back through this
guy
is hard
because the noise that we added
is comes from a Gaussian distribution.
There isn't a unique noise that could
have produced the X. All of these X hats
could have given you this X.
Right?
So, there isn't a single Z that could
have been that could have generated any
given X. What we need to characterize is
the collection of Zs that could all have
resulted in this X.
And so, there's an entire distribution
of Zs that could produce a given X. And
the distribution has a probability P of
Z given X.
So, we need to characterize this
somehow.
And
so, the encoder's job is not going to be
that of characterizing finding the
ex-specific Z for any X. It's going to
be characterizing the entire
distribution of Zs
for that X. And the way you're going to
train the model
in principle
is
this.
This is your decoder.
If you need if you knew the knew the Z
for every every X,
then you could put the Z through the
decoder, you have the X.
You minimize the error. This is your
standard
regression, right? Now, you don't know
the Zs. So, what we will do instead is
that you're going to put the X
through the encoder.
And it's going to give you a collection
of Zs, a distribution of Zs.
And then,
you're going to put this through the
decoder and it's going to give you X
hat. Except, you're going to put every
one of these Zs
through the decoder because they're all
possibilities, right?
Each of them is going to give you some
guess X hat.
And then you're going to minimize the
error over the set or the entire
distribution of Zs
that could
have generated this X. That making sense
to everybody? Right.
For that, we need to be able to do one
of two things. Either you want to be
able to mathematically characterize how
pushing the entire distribution through
the decoder works
or
you're going to have to you you won't
use all of them. You're going to pick
one of them. You're going to sample it
somehow.
And you're going to pass the sample
through the decoder.
Like is that making sense to you guys?
Guys on Zoom, that making sense?
Somebody say yes on Zoom, otherwise I'm
going to assume there's no one on Zoom.
Yes.
Okay, they're saying yes, okay.
Uh Professor, I have a question. Yeah.
Um
can we like make it so if there's
multiple classes with our data, we can
select the class when doing generation
or is this like only for a certain type
of data? There's no way to like
select certain class.
>> specific. We can definitely make it
class specific. And the way you would do
it it So, in the
Can you push postpone this to the end of
the class because I I want to finish
this lecture and then I'll answer that
question. It's a very it's a very nice
question, okay?
So, this is the variational autoencoder
because
again, finding a minimizing the error
over all possible Zs is challenging. So,
we're going to find a lower bound, a
variational lower bound and that's for
the error and that's what we're going to
Actually, it's
a variational upper bound to the error
and that's what we minimize or a
variational variational lower bound to
the likelihood, which is what we
maximize. And so, here's what we have.
The encoder computes the distribution of
Zs for any X. The decoder
decoder tries to convert the expected
output of all the Zs
to the target X.
Or more typically, it picks a random as
a
one sample from these Zs.
And so,
the overall training procedure is
the encoder has its own parameters
theta.
We have to
estimate the theta so that the Zs the
encoder produces
are going to become something like the
face we want, right?
Then, for the decoder, those Zs must be
put through the when when they go
through the decoder,
they must become faces. So, there are
two sides to it.
We have to learn this guy so that it
produces the right Zs.
And we have to learn this guy so that
those Zs become the face.
Make sense everybody, right? And then,
we have the constraint on the Z because
again, we can't just let this Z be any
odd thing. We want the Z to be standard
Gaussian.
So, the we're saying that now, for any
given X,
not all [clears throat] Zs are going to
give you that face.
The set of Zs that could give you that
face is going to be very restricted,
some small region in the overall
distribution of Zs, right? That's what
the encoder is doing. It's trying to
characterize this distribution.
But the overall distribution of Zs is a
standard Gaussian, right? And so, what
does that mean?
It It means that if you look at
the
conditional distribution of Zs
over all possible faces,
cumulatively, they've got to look like a
standard Gaussian.
That making sense?
Right? So, which means that if I
integrate P of Z given X over all
possible X's where some X's are more
probable than others,
this has to be a standard Gaussian. But
again, that's just integral of
P of X
P of Z given X
D
Z, was it DX, right?
Which is going to be integral of P of X
ZDX,
which we know is just P of Z.
We're saying this guy is standard
Gaussian, right? That's what this means.
Okay. So, we are going to try to
minimize the error
between this guy and the standard
Gaussian.
But we still have a problem.
And the problem is what the hell is P of
Z given X?
Now, if I take a sheet
and I fold it in some crazy way
and I make it some crazy manifold,
right? And so, I have this crazy man
manifolded sheet
and I'm saying that
and I've twisted and turned it in the
process of
modifying it. And I'm saying on the
twisted and turned region, this all this
portion of
this this space is going to become this
face.
When I go back into the input before
twisting and turning, can I actually
identify the corresponding region
in the planar version of Z
that could have given the face?
That's going to be very hard, right?
Because the whole thing was twisted and
turned and we have no idea how
untwisting it would work. So, that
decoder is a complicated function. I
don't know what this guy looks like.
It's definitely not going to look like a
Gaussian. It's going to be look look
some crazy some, you know,
of all possible Zs,
right? Maybe this little portion or
maybe this little portion is what became
a particular face.
But I have no no way of of determining
this, right?
So, we need to
So, the encoder has to characterize
this, but this can be all arbitrarily
ugly.
The encoder cannot actually characterize
it.
And so, we're going to do something.
We're going to approximate it. The way
we will approximate it is
I know what kinds of distributions I can
characterize.
And so, I'm going to carry I'm going to
come up with some distribution which
captures most of this,
but is as compact as possible
around the set of possible Zs that could
have generated a given face.
Again, that make any sense? Right?
And so,
this
means
how do I actually get a Q, an
approximation,
which is as close as possible to the P
of Z given X?
I want to minimize the
divergence
between my approximation and the true
guy, and I want to do this such that
this holds for most X's. So, I want to
do this minimize this diver expectation
of this divergence over all possible
X's. Right?
Make sense?
All right.
So,
this is what we're going to do.
Now, this is where the ugly math comes
in. The ugly math is follows.
If I look at the
Uh guys, if you have any doubts about
this so far, let me know.
Any questions?
Yes, no?
No, okay.
You're supposed to have questions. This
is some complicated stuff.
In my very first class at CMU, I had
this big kid who called himself Alpha
who came into my office after class.
He sat himself down,
and he said, "I have no questions
because I didn't understand a single
word."
Right? That's a perfectly valid thing to
do. I will spend time in correcting
things for you.
So, what is the KL divergence between
two distributions?
It's the expected
logarithm of the ratio of likelihoods
assigned to the data by
the two distributions. Right? So, it's
going to be the expectation over all Zs
drawn from Q, which is the
uh
approximation that you have, meaning the
expectation over all Zs from this guy.
You always want to take the larger one,
because if you take the smaller one,
everything that falls outside the
smaller one is going to give have like
negative infinity probabilities, you
know, log probabilities. You don't want
that. You always want to start with the
larger one.
And so, the expectation over all Zs from
Q
of the log of Q over P.
And, of course, that's the expectation
over all Zs
from Q of the log of Q minus the
expectation of the log of P.
We couldn't characterize this guy in the
first place. So, why are we back to this
one?
Well, we're going to use some base rule.
P of Z given X is P of X
P of Z times
P of X given Z divided by P of X. That's
just base rule, right? And so, when I do
this, I'm going to end up with
expectation over all Zs from Q of log of
Q
minus log of P
minus log of P of X given Z
plus log of
So, P of X, right?
Is this making sense to you guys over
here?
Now, if you take the first two terms,
the first two terms looks look like just
the second line in the slide.
So, the first two terms just give me the
KL divergence between
Q of Z for given X
and the and the P of Z, which is the
universal standard Gaussian. Right?
The second term over here is simply
uh expectation over Z of the log of P of
X given Z. It's the negative log
likelihood of X
for a given Z, which is X given This
This is going to look like the
distribution of the noise.
And the third term, this is just P of X.
P of X is not a function of any of the
network parameters. It's something that
we don't really need to worry about. And
so, the whole thing is simply going to
say,
"I'm going to find out
>> [snorts]
>> I'm going to find the decoder para uh
the
decoder parameters such that
the KL divergence between
the
approximation Q
and the standard Gaussian
minus the negative log log likelihood of
the data itself is minimized." Now, this
is about as complicated as the math
gets.
This making sense to everybody? Right?
Nothing fancy, right?
And so,
when I say that I want to make sure that
the average
of the posterior probabilities of Z
given X over all X's looks like a
standard Gaussian, instead of just the
having the true posterior probability,
I'm going to use the approximated
posterior probability, which is Q.
And so, now,
what exactly is this guy?
The average posterior probability
between
the average KL divergence between the
approximated posterior probability and
the standard Gaussian.
That I can just take this as
This is the expectation over X. That's
what the math tells us.
We as engineers know that any an
expectation is can always be
uh computed as an average over samples,
right? So, it's the average over all
training data
of the KL divergence between
the approximated posterior probability X
and the standard Gaussian.
That's the math, right?
And
this is what we're going to try to
minimize.
But we're still left with what is Q,
right? I just said I'm going to
approximate my posterior P of Z given X,
which I cannot characterize because
maybe it looks something like this
with a Q,
which is
maybe bigger than this guy, but
something I can characterize, then I can
compact it
so that it matches it as closely as
possible. Right? That's where we began.
Now, Q
is
Again, recall that Q must approximate P
of Z given X as closely as possible.
Now, we know the decoder is highly
non-linear.
It's difficult to characterize the
distribution of Z that could produce a
given X.
Now, also, we know that any given X is
going to have to come could have come
from a region
on the surface.
The manifold that's produced by the
decoder, right?
And yet,
if I actually knew the location
on the manifold that any given Z became,
then because I can add any odd noise,
there's a distribution of
faces that I could have generated from
this from this location depending on the
noise, and this distribution is simply
going to be the distribution of the
noise itself centered to
the location on the manifold, right?
>> [snorts]
>> And in any case, the point is we cannot
go back and find out what P of Z given X
is again.
Uh it's a very complicated slide stating
the obvious that if I have some region
on the surface on the curved surface,
there's no way for me to go back and say
over here it's this nice clean portion
of the original latent latent space,
right?
So,
we're going to
go back and So, we're going to look at
some mathematical
uh realities
to deal with this first.
What's the property of a standard
Gaussian? We said Z is a standard
Gaussian. It's an isotropic Gaussian,
right? Which means that regardless of
which direction you look at this
distribution from, it's going to look
like a standard Gaussian.
Secondly,
if I slice the standard Gaussian along
any plane at any plane,
this is a property of the standard
Gaussian. It's unstructured noise. It
doesn't matter how you look at it, it's
going to be unstructured. You're not
adding structure. If I cut it along a
line, a line is not providing any
information.
The distribution on that line is going
to be maximally unstructured. It's going
to be standard Gaussian. If I slice it
along a plane, it's going to be standard
Gaussian. That is the property of the
most unstructured noise you can think
of, right? So,
is that making sense to you guys? Right?
I can
And so, this property that is going to
hold regardless of the line or
hyperplane which you consider.
So, if I say I'm going to look at the
distribution of
this variable where X plus Y is three
or X1 plus X2 is three,
along that plane,
the distribution is going to be standard
Gaussian. I can say, you know, I can
draw any odd slice, and the distribution
is going to be standard Gaussian.
Because it's maximally unstructured.
That's why we wanted the unstructured
Gaussian because it's A,
it's making no assumptions about the
data.
B, by making no assumptions, it gives
you this very nice property, right?
Now, this has
a secondary
consequence. Instead of looking at a
plane, if I look at something that's
almost a plane, a mildly curved surface,
and if I look at the distribution along
the mildly curved surface, if the
surface is not curved too much, if it's
not varying too much from a plane,
on the mildly curved surface, the
distribution is going to be
approximately Gaussian.
Almost Gaussian. Is that making sense to
you guys? Right? And so, the only
difference is that if I choose a plane,
this Gaussian is going to be zero mean
unit variance.
If I choose a mildly curved surface, the
distribution on that
is going to be almost Gaussian, but the
mean won't be zero, and the variance
won't be one.
Right? That make any sense? Right. So,
uh
for nearly linear functions,
so what is a curved surface? A curved
surface is basically a surface of the
kind f of z equals zero or f of z equals
constant, right?
So, where for for nearly linear
functions,
the distribution on the curve
represented by this function
is going to be almost Gaussian,
but the mean and the variance of this
Gaussian are going to depend on the
function and where on the function
you're reading it.
Is that making sense to everybody?
But where's my yes?
Yes. Okay, thank you, right?
So,
we're going to use that.
And
here's your third poll.
Guys, if any of this is getting to be a
bit too dense, just let me know.
I can spend some time after class and go
go back and try to unravel the really
tangled bits.
I'm trying to make it easy, but
Okay, it's only two two two false
questions. What's the answer to the
first question?
Hm?
True. How many of you think it's true?
Okay, can everybody say true?
Thank you, right? What about the second
one? Just I'm not going to prompt you.
Everybody speak out the answer that you
think is correct together and we'll see
what the chorus sounds like. If it
sounds like noise, I've messed up,
right? 1 2 3.
Okay, great. [clears throat] We've done
a good job, right? The The z is a random
vector with an isotropic distribution.
The conditional distribution of the
projection on any affine plane is also
going to be isotropic Gaussian.
If z is a random vector with an
isotropic distribution, the conditional
distribution on any curved surface
of low curvature is also going to be
approximately Gaussian, right? And this
means that I can actually assume that my
approx This guy over here, if I can
assume that my
encoder is not folding the surface too
much in any given location, if the
curvature is low
over the head
space,
then I can approximate this guy
to be a Gaussian, right? I can say q is
Gaussian. If q is Gaussian, how do I
characterize a Gaussian?
What are the properties of a Gaussian?
Anyone?
Mean and variance.
>> Mean and variance, right? Now, I have a
mathematical formalism. All that needs
to do is
this guy, the encoder, just has to for
any given x, it only has to compute the
mean and the variance of this Gaussian.
Is that making sense? Right.
Now, once you do this,
we are So, we're approximating p of z
given x
as a Gaussian with a mean that's a
function of x and a variance that's a
that's that's a function of x.
And of course, the the
it's going to be mu of x semicolon phi.
Phi is the uh
represents the parameters of the network
that capture that computes the mean and
the variance.
Now,
the variance itself, there's no
restriction on the variance, but I'm
going to assume that the variances
diagonal variance because
mathematically, it's the most tractable
one.
And now, I'm going to use q
as a proxy of p, right?
So, we've figured out what the q looks
like, the approximation.
Now, next, we have to estimate the
parameters of the encoder
such that it computes a q
so that when I sample from this q
and pass it through the decoder, the
output looks like my training data, like
the face that I wanted to reconstruct.
Is that making sense, right? So,
we're going to do this and the
constraint, of course, is that the
average q of z given x has got to be as
close to Gaussian as possible.
How does that work?
Here's my q.
Here's my z. Z is coming from a standard
Gaussian.
Um z is coming from my q, not the
standard Gaussian, right? If q is a good
approximation,
then all z's that I draw from this q,
when passed through the decoder, must
generate an x that looks like my
training data, like my face.
Okay?
So,
furthermore, I'm going to assume that
this noise I can make any other
assumption about the noise itself over
here. And this this is math. But one of
the most simplifying assumptions is that
it's it's a
the noise that I have that that I must
add
to the output is also isotropic. The
reason, once again, isotropic
Gaussian means it's unstructured.
If that's unstructured, it means that
the model has captured most of the
structure on the data. So, we keep
falling back on this. We like using
isotropic Gaussians because if the model
actually generates errors that are
isotropic Gaussian, it means the model
has captured the structure in the data,
right?
So,
the probability of x given distribution
of x given z, you're just adding the
noise e to x hat.
If e is a Gaussian, this is just a
standard Gaussian. This is just a
Gaussian whose mean is at x hat
and the variance is sigma squared i,
right? So, I can write down the formula
for this, which is
uh the log probability of x.
This guy
given
that if I sample z from q,
the output of the decoder is going to be
x hat. If I give you this x hat for that
particular sample, what is the
probability that I will see this face?
That's going to What What is the
negative What is the log probability?
That's just given by this the log of the
Gaussian
computed with the mean at x hat.
And so,
I want to find out that encoder
parameters. Again, my job is to find the
and learn the encoder.
The encoder must compute this q
such that samples from q
give me, when transformed, look like my
face.
So, I'm not optimizing my decoder over
here. This is about optimizing my
encoder. I'm trying to find out how do I
optimize my encoder such that the
approximation q
gives me samples that look like my that
get transformed to my face,
right? And so, I'm going to be
maximizing the
log likelihood
of my data
given z's from this q.
And this I can do using back
propagation, right? I can instead of the
log likelihood, I can have the negative
log likelihood, which looks
like the formula over here. I can
minimize the negative log likelihood.
This looks more like a standard loss.
And then, subsequently,
you want to minimize this loss with
respect to the encoder parameters so
that it learns to compute the q
properly.
Does that make sense to everybody? It's
I know there are a lot of tangled
threads over here, but it's really not
that tangled.
I'm trying to learn the encoder so that
when I sample from the distribution
computed by the encoder and I pass those
samples through the decoder, it looks
like a face.
So, the way the way I will do it, I'm
going to
draw these samples, pass it through the
decoder, compute compare it to my face.
I have an objective, which is the error
between what the decoder produces and
the real face. I'm going to back
propagate it to fix my
encoder.
The specific loss that I chose over here
is the negative log likelihood. You
could choose something else.
The principle makes sense to everybody?
Right. Okay. And so,
now,
over here, we are sampling a z from q.
When I sample from from a distribution
and then pass it through the decoder,
sampling is a non-differentiable
process.
How do I back propagate through a
non-differentiable process? So, this is
where the standard the other
reparameterization method that people
like to harp about in VAEs comes in.
When I want to sample from a
non-standard Gaussian, if I have a
Gaussian somewhere,
right?
How do I sample from this? The way I
would do this
is I sample from a standard Gaussian,
then I scale the sample
such that the variance becomes like so
by multiplying it by the inverse
standard deviation, right? Or
multiplying it by the standard
deviation, right?
Which is the square root of the
variance.
And then,
add the mean so that the whole thing
goes out here.
So,
I can sample from a standard Gaussian
and like where is this?
This epsilon,
I multiply by the
inverse of the the square root of the
variance and then add the mean.
And that's going to give me a sample
from the target distribution that I
want.
But when I write it in this manner, my
mu and epsilon become part of my sample
and now this can be differentiated. I
can actually differentiate it with
respect to
I can I can differentiate the z with
the parameters of the encoder, theta,
right? So,
that's the sampling process that's
And now, so I can actually compute the
derivative of the loss that I got over
here with respect to the parameters of
the encoder by computing the derivative
with respect to z
and then multiplying the that by the
derivative of z with respect to the
uh encoder parameters, right?
So, chain rule.
Again, I don't expect you to get
everything, grasp everything as I
present it in class. There's a lot of
stuff.
But, if you're paying attention,
the general idea must be coming across
come across enough that when you go back
and look at the slides, it makes sense.
Right? Do you think you're there?
Yes, no?
Okay, you guys are very quiet.
Okay, let me try again. Yes or no?
And this is not working. Okay, my next
question needs I need I I really need a
very loud yes.
Keep in mind that I'm jet lagged. I've
just come back after 3 months of three
very horrendous months. I've traveled 68
hours to be here.
I'm more tired than you.
So, you must wake me up with your yes.
Okay? The second is how do I train the
decoder?
How do I estimate the phi?
So, let's say I've learned the encoder
properly. The encoder is doing a very
good job of
approximating the posterior probability
of Z given X.
So, anytime I sample from it,
the decoder must give me a good
face, right?
So, how do I
estimate the decoder? The way I do it,
this is like a standard regression,
right? I pass the Z through the decoder,
it's going to generate an output,
and I'm going to optimize my decoder so
that the noise that I must that I might
that I must add to account for the error
is as small as possible.
Right? Simple enough.
Or alternately, I'm going to do this by
saying that I if I assume some kind of a
distribution for the noise, I want the
variance of that distribution to be as
small as possible. That's how the I want
the the mean of the noise to be zero,
and the variance to be as small as
possible, right? That's how I make sure
that the noise is really small. So,
alternatively, that this means that when
I compute the probability of the noise
on a distribution, right? The the
distribution the probability must be as
high as possible because when the
probability is high, the variance is
small, right? As we're assuming that
it's a Gaussian distribution.
And for a Gaussian distribution, you
know this.
The Gaussian distribution has this
shape.
If the if the probabilities are low, the
variance is large.
If the probabilities are small, high,
the variance is small.
Because the the volume has to be one.
So, you're going to be learning the
model parameters to make the probability
of the noise as high as possible
while having a mean of zero.
That means that the spread of the noise
is as small as possible.
That makes sense to everybody?
And so, this
is just maximizing the
log probability or minimizing the
negative log probability of the noise.
And again, we know the distribution of
the noise. If I give you the Z, I give
you the X hat.
If I give you the X hat, then the
distribution of
the probability distribution of X is
just a Gaussian, which is the just the
distribution of the noise itself
with the mean shifted to X hat.
So,
I can which is that this term here,
I can compute the probability of X on
this distribution.
This is the negative log likelihood. I
want to minimize it. Alternately, I'm
maximizing the probability. That sounds
very mathy, but the basic idea is just
that.
I want to make the probability of the
noise as high as possible, which is the
error between
what the model computes and the true
data. I want it to have zero mean,
and I want the probability to be high.
That way I know that the spread of the
noise is as small as possible, right?
And so,
we want to
this NLL must now be
optimized with respect to the decoder
parameters.
So, here, of course, we have the final
constraint on Z, right? You want the
average uh
uh Q of Z to be as close to the standard
Gaussian as possible,
which means that
I want the KL divergence between
Q and the standard Gaussian to be
minimized. There's a formula for it.
I've written this on the slide. I'm not
going to read it out. I don't expect I
don't you expect you guys to
understand it or believe it. But then,
these days there's a magical tool,
you know, cloud.ai, Gemini,
right? dot.google.com.
So, you can actually ask it for the KL
divergence between two Gaussians, and
it's going to give you this formula. And
as we all know, these days you don't
need to derive anything, you just
believe Google, right?
So, that's what I did. Okay. Uh now,
this is a function of the encoder
parameters. And so, you have this whole
loss, which is actually it ends up
looking very much like a quadratic.
So,
all the terms that you end up with,
I've given you the logic behind every
term. I haven't actually derived the
math.
In my experience, anytime I do math on
the board, which I can,
nobody follows me, right? Uh what also
happens is that when I started at the
top left corner of the board and I get
to the bottom right, I have no idea what
I've been writing. It's I'm lost myself.
So, it's best that I just put it on the
slides. I expect you guys to go back and
take a look.
But, the idea that I used in deriving
these formulas should be clear.
Right?
And the simple
and the one extra thing is that this guy
error the error between the output of
the decoder and the true data, that's a
quadratic, right?
Uh this one,
the squared norm of the mean, that's a
quadratic, also.
Uh there's the log of the variance.
That's not a
And the trace the trace is a quadratic.
As it turns out, the log of the variance
is not, but it's differentiable.
And so, you end up with this nice loss
function, which captures everything that
we need. First, the the encoder must be
such that
samples drawn from the output of the
encoder when processed by the decoder
look like your data.
The decoder must be such that when these
samples are passed through the decoder,
they look like your data.
And then, the posterior probability must
be such that on average it looks like a
standard Gaussian.
These are the three principles that we
had, right? All three are captured by
this one simple loss.
And so, here is the overall model.
That makes sense to everybody?
Yes. Okay.
Thank you. Right? I don't expect the
math to make a lot of sense because
there's no way I'm going to convey that
much math in 70 minutes and have it make
sense.
But, the general principle makes sense,
right? And so,
uh here is
what you have. This is the encoder.
X goes in, it learns a Gaussian.
The Gaussian is approximating the
posterior probability of Z given X,
right?
Then, you're going to sample
a Z from this from this distribution.
Like I said, there are many Z's that
could have produced the X, you're
picking one at random, right?
And then, this sample is put through the
decoder,
which tries to generate a face.
And now, we have a loss
which quantifies the error with all the
constraints. It quantifies the error
that this guy makes in converting the Z
to the X.
It quantifies the error that this guy
makes in approximating the distribution
of Z
such that those Z's become the X. It
also quantifies the constraint on this Z
that the Z must be a standard Gaussian.
All of these three in one simple compact
loss.
Am I making sense? Right? Okay.
And that's what we minimize. Where are
the neural networks? This guy, of
course, is a neural net, and this is a
neural network two outputs, the mean and
the variance. Easy, right?
And
so, this is what it looks like. This
this encoder is a neural net, which
produces a mean
and a variance. It has a common set of
parameters.
And the decoder is also a neural
network, right?
And now, once you train it,
what was the point of this whole
process? All of this this exercise? The
point of this exercise was, you know, in
case you have forgotten,
uh we wanted to come up with a model
that you could sample,
that learns to characterize the
distribution of the data that you're
interested in or the particular class,
like faces,
and so that you could sample from it,
right? And the point were and and the
way we did it was that we had
uh we chose
the dimensionality of the manifold that
we thought the data lay on,
and we defined our latent variable
Z as a standard Gaussian
on this manifold. We wanted to put this
constraint on Z because if you didn't,
then you'd have no control over what
what value Z would take.
And then, we learned this model such
that this one would convert transform
this standard Gaussian
in the Z space, twisted and turned turn
the space so that it actually became a
distribution on the target manifold in
the
output space. And thereafter, you could
sample any sta- any Z from the standard
Gaussian, pass it through the decoder,
and the output would look like something
from your
uh target class. Say, a face, right?
And so, this was your decoder, right?
And the reason we needed the encoder was
that to do in order to learn the
decoder, you needed to know the Z for
every X.
And you needed to constrain some of the
Z. But, once the model has been trained,
you can throw the entire encoder
contraction out, and just the decoder
with the Z's
is going to give you a generative model.
Okay?
So,
this is the VAE. It's an autoencoder
with statistical constraints on the
hidden representation.
The encoder is a statistical model
that that computes the parameter of
parameters of a Gaussian that
approximates the posterior probability
of Z for any given X.
The decoder
converts samples from this hand. We
model it as a Gaussian because that's
most convenient. You could model it with
as anything else. You just have to adapt
the math for it. The principle still
hold, right?
And then the decoder converts samples
from the Gaussian back to the input.
And the decoder is a generative model
that when excited by samples from a
standard Gaussian
give you it gives you data from the last
that you're
interested in. Okay?
So, this is the variational autoencoder.
Again, the decoder is the actual
generative model.
The encoder is primarily needed for
training.
The encoder can also be used for other
purposes, right? Uh
so, what exactly would that be?
Is there an eraser here? Duster?
>> [clears throat]
>> So,
if you learn your model properly,
you expect some properties of
continuity. What do I mean by that?
In my Z space,
I have a standard Gaussian, which has an
isotropic distribution.
This Z
has been model modified by my decoder.
And now now I have this crazy surface,
right?
And this standard Gaussian now has maybe
become something like this over again,
maybe maybe maybe even have split into
different regions
because the decoder can do any odd
thing, right?
And uh anytime you sample from this Z
and pass it through the decoder, it's
going to pick samples from here or here
or here, which will give you a real
face, right?
Now, for if I choose any point over here
and any other point over here within the
Z,
and I traverse the line between the two,
the intermediate points must represent
some continuity some notion of
continuity in the latent space, right?
Now, what are these two guys?
What this means is that suppose I have
one X, X1 and X2,
and I put each of these through the
encoder,
X1 has a mean, which is maybe here.
Right? X2 has a mean, which is maybe
here.
If I choose a point somewhere on the
line,
if I've learned the model properly and
all the and the and the expected
continuity is held, then if I then this
point when passed through the decoder
must give you something that looks
halfway between X1 and X2, right? So,
you can also use this for those
purposes, right?
Yeah.
Track zone.
That's what you're here for.
Tracking zone.
All right, guys. First question, what's
the answer?
Hm? True.
True?
Uh the second question, what are the
true statements?
Anybody?
Yes.
All.
All?
Let's see.
Guys on Zoom, do you have an answer?
Anyone on Zoom? Hm? All. All. Okay,
let's see. Right, the variational
autoencoder is a generative extension of
autoencoders
that models probability distributions.
The standard VAE assumes a latent
representation that has an isotropic
Gaussian. It requires addition of
Gaussian noise to the output of a
regularized VAE in order to permit the
output to fill the space
beyond a lower dimensional manifold.
The decoder can be used to generate
samples from the distribution it's
trained on if the input is drawn from a
standard Gaussian. That was the idea,
okay?
So, when the paper first came out,
uh
they they were here some examples from
the paper. The top one, that's a VAE
trained on MNIST.
And then afterwards when they sample X
and sample Z and pass it through the
decoder, you can see that what comes out
actually looks like digits. Like it's
not digital like they're actual digits.
It's still done a very good job of
learning the distribution. The lower
one,
you know, they trained it on faces and
it kind of looks like faces. Does it
look like faces?
Right. What's wrong with this, though?
Something crazy about those faces?
Something off?
Or are they all just fine as faces?
Hm?
It's not that clear. It's not that
clear, right? Let me get back to that
point. That's something uh okay.
So, again, remember this thing I
mentioned where if you traverse two
points,
traverse the line between two points,
you should get some kind of a continuity
of variation. So, here's an example
where the thing was these two guys were
passed through the encoder.
And then if you pick intermediate points
on the line that connects the two means
and pass them through the decoder, it
actually kind of actually no, hear this.
This and this
>> [snorts]
>> were the two end points. The one in the
middle actually gives you a smiling
face, right? Uh or this and this.
The one in the middle gives you a
partially frowning face. It actually
captures the continuity of the manifold.
It's a it's it's it's quite impressive,
right? It does a very good job. This is
the foundation of much of what we do
with diffusion models and such like
today. So, it's something that you
really need to understand, okay?
So, it's a simple statistical extension
of the autoencoder. It's an excellent
generative model for uh I the
distribution of data P of X.
And someone asked me about, you know,
are these specific to a class? I'll get
I have a little time, I'll get back to
that. Right? But here are the
limitations.
We needed an approximation Q
because there was no way of
characterizing
what the reverse was. If you pass the
data back through the encoder or through
the decoder, what was the value of Z
that gave me this particular X?
There was no way of actually
characterizing this.
But what if I actually
put restrictions on my decoder on my
model so that for any given X, I could
go back and find the Z?
The answer is that if you can do that,
you end up with a model called a
normalizing flow model.
So, the normalizing flow is basically
just a variational autoencoder where the
decoder is invertible
so that you can find
the Z. Now, for this to be invertible,
right? What does it say about the
dimensionality of Z versus the
dimensionality of X?
Anyone?
They have to be the same, which means
you're not making any low dimensional
manifold assumptions on Z, right?
Nonetheless, the model actually learns
the restrictions on Z if you train it
properly. So, it's pretty powerful.
The other thing is this guy, right? In
the pictures that we saw,
these guys were not
They're supposed to be faces,
but they're not really looking like
faces, right? I mean, they're fuzzy
faces.
What does it mean? Now, in our
encoder in our model,
we had this assumption that
when you train the model,
Z goes in,
then the decoder, which is actually a
generative model, produces an X.
And then to get the actual X hat, to get
the actual X, you had to add
an uncorrelated isotropic Gaussian
noise, correct?
Noise.
That means the noise that you add to X
hat doesn't look anything like faces.
That's the model, right? If that's that
were true,
then these should have been noisy faces
with speckled Gaussian like Gaussian
like noise, right?
But if I were to take an underlying face
for each of these guys and look at the
difference, do you think the difference
would be face like or is it going to be
noise like?
What would it look like?
This looks like a fuzzy face, right?
What's the difference between a fuzzy
face and a clear face?
Is it going to be noise or is it going
to have face like structures?
Noise? Not necessary not really, right?
You get all the
uh you know, outlines are gone, the
structures are gone. All of those are
very face like, correct?
So, the reason this thing looks kind of
blurry
is that if you look at the difference
between this eye and a real eye, that's
where some of the some of what makes an
eye an eye is captured, right? So, the
noise is not really uncorrelated. It's
not independent. No matter how well you
train the model, it hasn't actually
managed to become independent.
The reason for that is that traversing
the distribu- the gap from Z all the way
to the distribution of X a standard
Gaussian to a distribution of X, that's
a huge gap.
The model is not able to do this
properly.
The model would do it prop- better if
the Z were closer to the distribution of
faces in the first place, right? Where
could such a distribution be obtained
from?
A distribution that is closer to
distribution of faces.
Anyone?
How about this guy?
This guy is actually giving you
something that's not quite the
distribution of faces,
but it's like faces, right? So, which
means that I can actually have
a VAE out here,
and the output of that guy is going to
be closer to the distribution of faces,
right? But then that's going to have the
same problem. So, I can keep nesting
things.
And so, when I nest
VAEs one inside another and place some
restrictions on the nesting, you end up
with what's called a diffusion model.
And uh nested VAEs
with the restriction on linearity end up
with a diffusion model. We'll cover
these in the next class.
Sorry for going over. Thank you.
Thank you, guys.
And it's good to finally see all of you
in person.
>> [clears throat]